dondavis computer science education specialist

about

san antonio, texas

dondavis@reglue.org misterdavis.org academia edu://DDavis linkedin://don-davis

languages

english german basic spanish

programming

Alice, Kodu, Scratch, IPRO

Regular Expressions

Python, R

SQL, Bash, HTML, NetLogo JavaScript (including

jQuery, D3), Ruby on Rails, embedded C, Java interests

developing, designing, and researching environments and pedagogy to support underrepresented students' computer science identity and skills trajectories, relational frame theory, embodied cognition, behavioral economics, social network analysis, data mining, learning analytics

education

2011 -

present Ph.D. in progress, coursework complete University of Texas at San Antonio

Interdisciplinary Learning and Teaching

leveraging embodied cognition to support CS identity and skill trajectories

2011 M.Ed. Texas State University

Educational Technology

cognate focus on English Language Learners

2002 **B.A.** University of Texas at Austin

English/German minor:linguistics

1999/2000 - Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Computer Science and Older German Literature

university employment history

08/2013 -

present University of Texas at San Antonio University Teaching Fellow

Fall 2013 - Teaching assistant multidisciplinary research seminar

Spring 2014 - developed, piloted protocol for evaluating dept's online content

01/2013 -

08/2013 Wisconsin Center for Education Research Research project manager / assistant researcher

Funded by the Collaborative Research: Programming Standing Up (NSF) grant. identified computational thinking/computer science learning progressions and collaborative

learning processes using Educational Data Mining (EDM) and learning analytics.

08/2011 -

12/2012 **University of Texas at San Antonio** research assistant, student teacher supervisor, instructor

research assistant - funded by the NSF to investigate facilitating computational thinking

and computer science skills in novices

student teacher supervisor - supervised student teachers in the San Antonio area

instructor - IDS 2012, "Diversity in the Classroom"

K12 employment history

08/2006 -

05/2011 San Marcos High School Newcomer/ESL Instructor, Campus ESL Facilitator, LPAC chair

taught content area English to recent immigrants, supported faculty with providing appropriate instruction for English learners, documented and tracked English Learner progress

at the campus level

08/2005 -

05/2006 **Granger Independent School District** 7th, 8th, and 11th Grade English Teacher

facilitated students' critical reading and composition skill development

08/2002 -

05/2005 **The New School, Berlin, Germany** English as a Foreign Language Teacher

developed and instructed a variety of English courses, e.g., English for beginners, ad-

vanced English for business purposes, etc.

societal affiliations

10bitworks Makerspace
Alamo City Behavior
Analysts (ACBA)
Association for Computing
Machinery (SIGCSE,
SIGCAS)

Texas Computer Education Association (SOSSIG) Association for the

Advancement of Computing in Education (AACE)

Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education (SITE) Texas Teachers of English to Speakers of Other

Languages (TexTESOL)

journal articles

articles in peer-reviewed journals

AMOEBA - facilitating data-driven, real time novice programmer collaboration

Matthew Berland, Davis, Don, Carmen Smith

in review (2014). 2014

Strengthening listener behavior through auditory conditional discrimination training

Lee Mason, Alonzo Andrews, Davis, Don

in review (2014). 2014

A model of how children approach engineering design in robotics

Timothy Yuen, Davis, Don, Jenifer Stone, A Guillen, Erin Price, A Gomez

in review (2014). 2014

Using learning analytics to understand the learning pathways of novice programmers

Matthew Berland, Taylor Martin, Tom Benton, Carmen Petrick Smith, Davis, Don

Journal of the Learning Sciences 22.4 (2013) pp. 564-599. 2013

Supporting English learners with participatory augmented reality simulations

Davis, Don, Matthew Berland

On the Horizon 21.4 (Sept. 20, 2013) pp. 294-303. 2013

international peer-reviewed conference proceedings

Multiple case study of nerd identity in a CS1 class

Davis, Don, Timothy Yuen, Matthew Berland

Proceedings of the 45th ACM technical symposium on Computer science education, 2014

Visualizing live collaboration in the classroom with AMOEBA

Matthew Berland, Carmen Smith, Davis, Don

Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on Computer Supported Collaborative Learning (CSCL 2013), 2013, Madison, Wisconsin

Monsterismus: Recursively relevant CS game design

Matthew Berland, Timothy Yuen, Davis, Don

Proceedings of the Games, Learning, & Society Conference 8.0, 2013, Madison, WI

Learning in the GNU/Linux community

Davis, Don, Iffat Jabeen

Proceedings of the 2011 conference on Information technology education, 2011, New York, NY, USA

Legitimate peripheral participation in the GNU/Linux community

Davis, Don, Iffat Jabeen

Proceedings of Society for Information Technology & Teacher Education International Conference 2011, 2011, Nashville, TN

Through the looking glass [using Alice with newcomers]

Davis, Don

Proceedings of Society for Information Technology & Teacher Education International Conference 2010, 2010, San Diego, CA

additional conference presentations

2011	Learning in the GNU/Linux community presented with Iffat Jabeen Texas Linux Fest
2010	Linux LTSP: Revitalize Old Hardware Texas Computer Education Association TCEA State Conference
2010	Alice: Multimedia Storytelling the Easy Way trained educators on using Alice to illustrate narratives while introducing CS/CT concepts
2010	Through the looking glass: Multimedia presentations with Alice edTech10: Becoming 21st Century Change Agents; Texas State University, San Marcos, Texas
2008	iPods in the Newcomer classroom presented with Nicki Konecki and Rosa Aponte-Gonzalez Textesol

Berlin, Germany 7 years

international

grant writing experience

- Co-author* of Makescape, interactive hybrid virtual informal learning environment to support engineering career trajectories for students underrepresented in STEM. Grant proposal for NSF (\$591,528) with Matthew Berland, Univ. of Wisconsin-Madison and Leilah Lyons, Univ. of Illinois at Chicago [Accepted]
- Co-author* of Mapping the Participation of Hispanic Students in Computer Science (MaPHiCS).
 Grant proposal for NSF (\$100,000) with Matthew Berland, Univ. of Wisconsin-Madison and Alex
 J. Bowers, Columbia University
- PI for **The Freedom Toaster Project: Free and Open Source Software for All**. Made kiosk to distribute free and open source software in a high school. Grant funded by A+FCU. (\$1000; 2008)
- PI for **Access for All**. provided internet access to a primarily Hispanic, recent immigrant community using a student made mesh network. Grant funded by A+FCU. (\$1000; 2007, renewed 2008)

honors

- · Alpha Chi Honor Society, September 2010 May 2011
- · Golden Key International Honour Society, September 2010 May 2011
- · Dean's List. University of Texas at Austin, 2001, 2002

appointments

- · Member, San Marcos High School Campus Leadership Team, October 2010 May 2011
- Member, Continuing Improvement Plan District Committee. San Marcos Consolidated Independent School District, September 2010 May 2011
- · Chairperson, Language Proficiency and Assessment Committee, San Marcos High School, San Marcos, Texas, 2008-2011

professional service activities

2013,2014	Event Volunteer Madison, Wisconsin	Games and Learning Society (GLS) 9.0,10.0 Conference
2013,2014	Guest Reviewer Madison, Wisconsin	GLS 9.0, 10.0
2011	Technical Reviewer Birmingham, UK: Packt Publish	The Alice 3 Cookbook

*Graduate students cannot be Co-Pls on NSF funded grant proposals.

volunteer work

- · Unconference organizer for OpenEdJAM (December 2013 Present)
- · Technologist for Alamo City Behavior Analysts (July 2013 Present)
- · Mentor. Beacon Hill Elementary, San Antonio, Texas. (2013)
- · Science fair judge. Science Hall Elementary, Buda, Texas. (2012).
- Hispanic Heritage Month Committee Member (2008, 2009) / Lead (2007, 2010), San Marcos High School, San Marcos, Texas. (2007 – 2011)
- · Linux Against Poverty Repair team member (August, 2009); Install Team Lead (June 2010)
- · reglue.org (501c3) Founder (2007), Board member (January 2007 August 2010)
- · San Marcos High School Linux Users Group Sponsor (September 2010 May 2011)
- · Hispanic Heritage Month Student Club Sponsor (September 15 October 15, 2007)
- · WEP club (Wireless Education Project) Faculty Sponsor (August 2007 May 2009)
- · Provided Lesson Plan Generator to Faculty of San Marcos High School (November 2007)